Guide to the Debra Bergen Koster Papers WAG.369
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Debra Bergen Koster Papers
1977-2017
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Koster, Debra Bergen
WAG.369
2.25 linear feet in 4 manuscript boxes and 1 half manuscript box
255.3 kilobytes in 14 computer files
Debra Bergen Koster (known as Debra Bergen) is a retired labor organizer and labor educator. She entered the labor movement as an organizer in the 1980s with SEIU District Council 925 and NYC Women Office Workers, a local of 9to5, National Association of Working Women. From 1983 to 1986 she then organized and represented home care and hospital workers with Local 1199, National Union of Health Care and Hospital Employees (SEIU 1199). Beginning in 1987 she held the position of Contract Administrator at the Doctors Council, SEIU. Koster later served as the Director of Contract Administration for the PSC/CUNY, Local 2334, NYSUT, AFT from 1991-2018. For 20 years she was an Adjunct Instructor in the Cornell NYS ILR Trade Union Certificate for Women and Labor Studies programs and co-coordinated and taught at the United Association for Labor Education (UALE) Union Summer Schools for Working Women. The Debra Bergen Koster Papers (dated 1977-2013) consists of materials created and collected by Koster documenting her activities as a labor organizer and labor educator, with particular emphasis on fair contract negotiations and support for women workers on issues such as pay equity, discrimination, and sexual harassment. Materials documenting Koster's activities as a labor educator include course materials and notebooks, many of which are from Cornell University's Trade Union Studies Program. This collection also includes materials documenting union leadership campaigns and elections through ephemera, petitions, and correspondence. Materials documenting her organizing activities and contract administration with Local 1199, National Union of Hospital and Healthcare Workers include correspondence, background subject files, and a signed summary of tentative agreement.
Scope and Contents
The Debra Bergen Koster Papers (dated 1977-2013) consists of materials created and collected by Koster documenting her activities as a labor organizer and labor educator, with particular emphasis on fair contract negotiations and support for women workers on issues such as pay equity, discrimination, and sexual harassment. Materials documenting Koster's activities as a labor educator include course materials and notebooks, many of which are from Cornell University's Trade Union Studies Program or her involvement with 9to5, National Association of Working Women. This collection also includes materials documenting union leadership campaigns and elections through ephemera, petitions, and correspondence. Materials documenting her organizing activities and contract administration with Local 1199, National Union of Hospital and Healthcare Workers include correspondence, background subject files, and a signed summary of tentative agreement.
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist. The materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Debra Bergen Koster in March 2022; the accession number associated with this gift is 2022.022.
Born-Digital Access Policies and Procedures
Advance notice is required for the use of computer records. Original physical digital media is restricted. An access terminal for born-digital materials in the collection is available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only. Researchers may view an item's original container and/or carrier, but the physical carriers themselves are not available for use because of preservation concerns.
Biographical Note
Debra Bergen Koster (known as Debra Bergen) is a retired labor organizer and labor educator. She entered the labor movement as an organizer in the 1980s with SEIU District Council 925 and NYC Women Office Workers, a local of 9to5, National Association of Working Women. From 1983 to 1986 she then organized and represented home care and hospital workers with Local 1199, National Union of Health Care and Hospital Employees (SEIU 1199). Beginning in 1987 she held the position of Contract Administrator at the Doctors Council, SEIU. Koster later served as the Director of Contract Administration for the PSC/CUNY, Local 2334, NYSUT, AFT from 1991-2018. For 20 years she was an Adjunct Instructor in the Cornell NYS ILR Trade Union Certificate for Women and Labor Studies programs and co-coordinated and taught at the United Association for Labor Education (UALE) Union Summer Schools for Working Women. She retired in 2017.
Labor -- Education.; Women -- Employment -- United States.; Labor unions -- Contract administration.; Women labor union members -- New York (N.Y.); Grievance procedures |z United States.; Sexual harassment.; Women in the labor movement -- United States; Women's rights.; Koster, Debra Bergen; 9 to 5, National Association of Working Women (U.S.); 1199, National Health and Human Service Employees Union; Professional Staff Congress/City University of New York
- Labor Program -- Advancing the World of Work -- Arbitration, 2003-2004 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- 31st United Association for Labor Education (UALE) Summer Institute for Working Women, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
- UALE Summer School, 2008-2009 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Working Women Curriculum, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Northeast Regional Summer School for Union Women, 2013-2014 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- PSC Labor Education, 2001-2012 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Session I Materials, 1999-2004 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Cornell University Institute for Women and Work; Labor Liberal Arts Program, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Doctors Council, 1977-1989 (Box 2, Folder 4-13)
- "Did You Get MY Message" Symposium, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Civil Service Issues, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Labor Program -- Advancing the World of Work -- Leadership, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Labor Program -- Advancing the World of Work -- Labor Law, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Grievance Training, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Labor Studies Certificate Program -- Union Administration Course Packet, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Women Fighting Poverty Conference, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- SEIU Local 203, 1981-1982 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Ephemera, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Rosie the Riveter, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Labor History Committee Meeting Outlines, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Women Office Workers, 1979-1981 (Box 3, Folder 8-9)
- District 1199 (Hospital and Healthcare Employees Union), 1986 (Box 3, Folder 10-11)
- Website Content, 2007 (Box 3, Folder 12, Box Electronic Records, Item TW_WAG_369_ER_1)
- Certificates, 1981-2013 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Women Office Workers, undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Women Office Workers, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Training Materials: Grievances, Sexual Harassment, 1993-1998 (Box 4, Folder 2-4)
- Women's Labor Issues (Includes Sexual Harassment), 1981-1992 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Labor Education Materials, 1990-1993 (Box 4, Folder 6-7)
- Collective Bargaining, 1999-2008 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Collective Bargaining Agreements, 1995-2017 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Contract Workshop Materials, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Theory and Practice of Labor Relations (Course Taught by Debra Bergen), 1993 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- AFSCME Steward Handbook, 2003 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Cornell Labor Studies Certificate Program, 2001-2006 (Box 5, Folder 2)